Let’s say you’re trying to
find some solid information
about a serious health
problem that concerns you,
like high blood pressure,
or diabetes.
Yet, everywhere you look,
someone’s trying to sell you
something like vitamins,
yoga mats, blenders, drugs.
Well, breathe a
sigh of relief
because all we bring
you are the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we talk about the best way to
manage the symptoms of menopause,
starting with the management
of genitourinary symptoms.
Typically starting about four
to five years after their last period,
about half of postmenopausal women
suffer from what we used to call
vulvovaginal atrophy,
now referred to by the name
GSM, genitourinary syndrome
of menopause,
thanks to the Vulvovaginal Atrophy
Terminology Consensus Conference
who needed a more
“publicly acceptable term.”
After all, the word atrophy
had “negative connotations,”
and the word vagina “is not a generally
accepted term for public discourse.”
They liken it to the shift
from the “pejorative”
impotence to “erectile dysfunction.”
Whatever you call it,
it involves changes to the vulva
(the external genitalia), the vagina
(the birth canal), and bladder,
caused by menopausal
changes in hormone levels.
Vaginal symptoms include vaginal
dryness, burning, itchiness
and irritation, pain
during penetrative sex,
and post-coital bleeding
from the thinning
of the vaginal lining.
Urinary symptoms can include recurrent
bladder infections and incontinence.
Some women with mild GSM
remain asymptomatic.
For others, symptom severity
can preclude intercourse altogether
and result in discomfort
even with just sitting or wiping.
In a survey of thousands
of women with GSM,
59 percent said their symptoms
“considerably decreased
their enjoyment
of sexual activity,” and 23 percent
reported having
an adverse effect on their
“general enjoyment of life.”
While other menopausal symptoms
like hot flashes
tend to improve over time,
GSM symptoms tend to get
progressively worse.
Unfortunately, women
rarely seek medical help,
even though there are safe
and simple treatments available.
The first-line treatment for mild
to moderate vaginal dryness
are lubricants and moisturizers.
Lubricants are designed to reduce
friction during sexual activity,
whereas vaginal moisturizers
are used on a regular basis
(daily or every two
to three days as needed)
to provide day-to-day
comfort by mimicking
normal vaginal secretions
regardless of sexual activity.
Water-based lubricants
have the advantage
of being non-staining
and are associated
with fewer genital symptoms
such as discomfort or burning,
compared to silicone-
based lubricants.
What’s the best vaginal moisturizer?
This head-to-head study pitted
vaginal estrogen versus Replens,
an expensive vaginal moisturizer
claiming special
“bioadhesive” ingredients,
versus a placebo gel
of hydroxyethylcellulose,
which is found in products
15 times cheaper like K-Y Jelly.
After 12 weeks, the researchers
found no difference
between any of them—
they all worked the same.
This “striking
double-negative finding”
led to an accompanying commentary
in the American Medical Association
journal to conclude
that until there is evidence
to suggest otherwise,
“postmenopausal women
experiencing vulvovaginal symptoms
should choose the cheapest
moisturizer or lubricant
available over the counter”
instead of wasting your money.
That was for efficacy, though.
What about safety?
The World Health Organization
recommends, based on the SMI test,
that personal lubricants
and vaginal moisturizers
not exceed an osmolality of 380.
That’s a measure of how concentrated
the dissolved components are.
How did they come up
with that number?
By lubing up slugs.
SMI stands for slug
mucosal irritation.
They cover slugs with lubricant
over a five-day period
and measure how much
mucosal irritation
and tissue damage
the slug experiences.
No adverse effects
below the 380 cut-off,
but something like K-Y Jelly
at over 2,000
induced mild to moderate irritation,
and something off the charts
like Astroglide at 5,000+ caused severe
irritation and tissue damage.
Dozens of commonly used lubricants
and moisturizers available world-wide
have been put to the test,
and the only two vaginal moisturizers
that met the WHO criteria
were the Yes brand
aloe vera gel-based moisturizer
and the Balance Activ brand
hyaluronic acid-based one.
The only lubricants that made
the cut were those made
by brands Yes, Good Clean Love,
System Jo, and one product by Durex,
their Sensilube gel, but not
their Play Feel lubricant.
In our next story,
we find out if vaginal estrogen carries
the same risk as oral estrogen.
The first-line treatment
for mild to moderate vaginal dryness
due to menopause are lubricants
and moisturizers.
If over-the-counter lubricants
and moisturizers are insufficient
to control the genitourinary
symptoms of menopause, low-dose,
local estrogen therapy
is recommended,
unless women have a history
of hormone-dependent cancers
like endometrial or breast.
Local, meaning applied vaginally,
as opposed to taken orally.
Vaginal application is considered
safer and more effective
than systemic hormone therapy.
A meta-analysis of 58 studies
comparing vaginal
to systemic estrogens
found that vaginal estrogen therapy
offered better symptom relief
than estrogen pills, patches, or implants.
In fact, many women who are on systemic
menopausal hormone therapy
have to add on supplemental vaginal
estrogens to control symptoms.
Vaginal estrogens are available
as a variety of creams,
suppositories, and rings.
Thirty randomized, control comparative
trials have been performed,
and there appears to be
no difference in efficacy
between the various preparations.
However, they may take weeks
before a noticeable alleviation
of symptoms is detected,
and two to three months
before the full effect is achieved.
Although year-long studies
can clearly demonstrate
vaginal estrogen’s benefit,
studies as long as 12 weeks
have failed to manifest
superiority to placebo.
Some of the estrogen applied
to the vulva or vagina
is systemically absorbed
and therefore convey
the same black box FDA notice
that oral estrogens carry,
an all-caps warning of increased risk
of “endometrial cancer,
cardiovascular disorders, breast cancer
and probable dementia.”
Vaginal estrogen
is considered safer, though,
since it can be used
at a much lower dose
(as low as one-hundredth the oral dose).
The Harvard Nurse’s Health Study
did not find any increased risks
associated with vaginal estrogen use
over 18 years of follow-up.
Randomized controlled trials
lasting up to a year
appear to confirm its safety,
but there have been observational
studies linking vaginal use
to about a doubling of odds
for endometrial cancer,
but this was done
back in the 1970s
when higher estrogen doses
were used.
And a more recent study out of Denmark
that found the same thing
may have been confounded
by concurrent oral estrogen exposure.
Out of an abundance of caution, though,
even low-dose localized estrogen
may be contraindicated
in hormone-dependent cancer survivors
to be on the safe side.
Breast cancer survivors
suffering from GSM
may want to consider
vaginal DHEA instead.
Oral DHEA doesn’t appear
to offer any benefit,
but in 2016 the FDA approved vaginal
DHEA suppositories for pain
during intercourse due to menopause.
It’s converted locally into estrogen
and does not significantly
affect systemic hormone levels.
A downside is that it has to be
administered nightly,
whereas estrogen preparations
are typically twice a week,
or even every few months
with the vaginal rings.
For those who would rather
have an oral treatment,
there is ospemifene,
a tamoxifen-type drug
that has pro-estrogenic effects
on the vaginal lining.
However, it can actually double
the rate of hot flashes
and urinary tract infections
in the short-term,
and insufficient data is available
for long-term safety.
Did you know that soy foods may
explain why Japanese-American women
not only have the lowest rates
of hot flashes in the United States
but also have the lowest
rates of vaginal dryness.
Here’s the story.
One consensus panel
of experts concluded
that soy can be considered
a first-line treatment
for menopausal hot flash
and night sweat symptoms.
What about for vaginal dryness?
There have been a few studies
on the topical application
of soy isoflavone vaginal gels,
which in general have shown
beneficial effects, for example,
showing a significant improvement
in dryness and pain-with-intercourse
over placebo gels.
In fact, they’re roughly
on par with estrogen cream
in a head-to-head test.
But what about just eating soy?
Soy isoflavones improve female
sexual dysfunction of mice,
significantly increasing
vaginal blood flow,
but what about in people?
The data using isolated soy
supplements is mixed.
Some studies totally flopped,
showing no benefit over placebo,
all the way up to studies
showing comparable efficacy
when pitted head-to-head
against hormone therapy
for both hot flashes and muscle pain,
as well as vaginal dryness,
with no significant differences
between the two.
And of course, soy has the benefit
of “no increased risk of breast
and uterine cancer
or cardiovascular disease,”
unlike systemic hormonal
menopause therapy.
What about soy foods, though,
rather than soy supplements?
Well, there was a muffin study.
Women randomized
to daily muffins
containing soy flour
or ground flaxseeds
saw no difference
in menopausal sexual symptoms
compared to wheat
flour placebo muffins.
Similarly, women randomized
to 12 weeks of a daily scoop
of soy protein powder experienced
a significant improvement
in sexual quality
of life symptoms,
but not compared
to the milk protein control group.
What about soymilk?
There have been three studies.
Compared to women
randomized to drink
about two cups of dairy milk
a day for eight months,
those randomized to soymilk
ended up with significantly fewer
menopausal sexual symptoms,
though this appeared to be more
due to symptoms
getting worse on the dairy
than getting better on the soy.
That reminds me of a study
in Thailand where women
randomized to a soy-free diet
experienced a worsening
of vaginal dryness and overactive
bladder-type symptoms,
but adding extra soy didn’t seem
to make them better.
The second soymilk study
found about two cups a day
over two months appeared to drop
vaginal and sexual symptoms
by a whopping 60 to 70 percent
compared to the do-nothing
control group,
but since the control group
didn’t drink anything special,
it’s impossible to rule out
placebo effects.
The latest study found significant
improvements in sexual symptoms
after just six weeks of less than
a cup of soymilk a day,
but again, the control group
did nothing.
So, does soymilk work?
We really don’t know,
but it can’t hurt to give it a try—
unless you overdo it.
A 44-year-old New Yorker
presented to her gynecologist
with an “increase in desire
that required her to self-stimulate
to orgasm
approximately 15 times daily.”
It turns out, a month
before she started eating
in excess of four pounds
of soy foods a day.
Thankfully, within three months
of cutting back,
her desire cooled
to the point that she was able
to “engage in satisfying sexual activity
only twice daily.”
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books were
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of “How Not to Age”.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.